<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://sdbrenner.github.io//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://sdbrenner.github.io//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-06-10T16:19:21-07:00</updated><id>https://sdbrenner.github.io//feed.xml</id><title type="html">s.d.brenner</title><subtitle>Samuel Brenner's research</subtitle><entry><title type="html">presentation at osm2022</title><link href="https://sdbrenner.github.io//posts/2022-01-01-osm2022" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="presentation at osm2022" /><published>2022-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://sdbrenner.github.io//posts/osm2022</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sdbrenner.github.io//posts/2022-01-01-osm2022">&lt;p&gt;I’ll be presenting at the 2022 virtual Ocean Sciences Meeting. Watch my presentation to learn about the work I’ve been doing to understand the sea ice and ocean mixed layer inertial oscillations.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presentation will be in the High Latitude session HL15: &lt;em&gt;Air-Ice-Ocean Interactions in a Changing Arctic&lt;/em&gt;. The conference abstract can be found here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://osm2022.secure-platform.com/a/gallery/rounds/3/details/3510&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seasonal variations of inertial velocities of sea ice and ocean surface layer in the Beaufort Sea&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and is copied below&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous studies have shown strong seasonal differences in the strength of inertial-frequency currents in the surface mixed layer of the Arctic, with relatively lower energy during the winter ice-covered period. These past observations suggest that sea ice inhibits the transfer of momentum from the wind into the ocean. As the Arctic sea ice pack shifts to a more seasonal regime, there are questions about what impact that will have on wind-driven velocities in the upper ocean. In this study, we use observations of sea ice and the upper ocean from a series of moorings in the Beaufort Sea to better understand atmosphere-ice-ocean momentum transfer, with a particular focus on the inertial-frequency response. These observations are interpreted using a simple 1D ice-ocean coupled “slab” model. Despite its simplicity, the model provides insight into some of the processes driving the observations and the differences between the moorings. We find that seasonality of near-surface currents is driven primarily by a combination of sea ice internal stresses and seasonal variations in the mixed layer depth. The parameterized strength of the sea ice internal stresses (represented by a linear damping coefficient) vary between moorings and have a strong dependence on sea ice concentration. Below ~80%-90% concentration, the ice moves in free drift and provides no damping on the mixed-layer inertial currents. Comparisons between the moorings show that inertial currents at the southernmost mooring (within the seasonal ice zone) are already minimally impacted by presence of sea ice even during the winter ice pack. Nonetheless, seasonal velocity variations are still present there due to the changes in mixed-layer depth.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ll be presenting at the 2022 virtual Ocean Sciences Meeting. Watch my presentation to learn about the work I’ve been doing to understand the sea ice and ocean mixed layer inertial oscillations.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">new paper on ice-ocean drag</title><link href="https://sdbrenner.github.io//posts/2021-04-01-new-paper" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="new paper on ice-ocean drag" /><published>2021-04-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://sdbrenner.github.io//posts/new-paper</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sdbrenner.github.io//posts/2021-04-01-new-paper">&lt;p&gt;I’m excited to share that my paper has been accepted in &lt;em&gt;JGR: Oceans&lt;/em&gt;. Learn about how Arctic sea ice geometry influences the transfer of momentum across the ice-ocean interface, and how well that’s described by current theories.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1029/2020JC016977&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comparing observations and parameterizations of ice-ocean drag through an annual cycle across the Beaufort Sea&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used observations from moorings to investigate ice-ocean drag over the course of a year and saw consistent seasonal signals with a minimum drag in the summer/fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/figures/drag_timeseries.png&quot; alt=&quot;Timeseries of ice-ocean drag measurements&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Direct measurements of ice geometry allowed us to compare these results to parameterizations used in modern sea ice models (e.g, such as the one introduced for CICE). Together, the observations and model parameterizations showed that the seasonal signals that were tied to the growth and melt of ice keels; when the keels melted, the drag coefficients significantly decreased.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, a positive outlook for the parameterizations we tested:  they were able to predict the drag coefficients when the real ice geometry was used as input. BUT there were challenges in predicting geometry from bulk measures (especially floe sizes during melt season). This may explains the seasonal mismatch seen between past observations/model results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully these results can be used to improve models of sea ice dynamics, and to better constrain the surface boundary conditions when looking at things like upper ocean shear-driven mixing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’m excited to share that my paper has been accepted in JGR: Oceans. Learn about how Arctic sea ice geometry influences the transfer of momentum across the ice-ocean interface, and how well that’s described by current theories.</summary></entry></feed>